[音乐]&gt；&gt；道格拉斯：让我给你一个类比
[MUSIC] &gt;&gt; Douglas: Let me give you an analogy
来自视觉处理。
from visual processing.
视觉处理是计算机图形学的对立面。
Visual processing is the opposite of computer graphics.
在那里你可以从摄像机中获取信号并分析所有的像素
It's where you take a signal from a camera and analyze all the pixels and
尝试确定场景中的所有对象是什么
try to determine what are all the objects in the scene and
它们在摄像机中是如何相对于彼此移动的。
how are they all moving relative to each other in the camera.
你需要能够解决这个问题才能在这个世界上行走
You need to be able to solve this problem in order to walk in the world and
这是一个非常困难的问题。
it's a really really difficult problem.
但我们都能解决。
But we're all able to solve it.
事实上，所有的动物都能解决这个问题。
And in fact all the animals are able to solve it.
我们之所以能做到这一点，是因为我们没有解决一般的问题
And the reason we're able to do that is because we don't solve the general problem
因为一般的问题很难。
because the general problem is hard.
相反，我们解决特殊问题。
Instead we solve special problems.
更容易解决的问题，但有时会给出错误的答案。
Problems which are much easier to solve, but which sometimes give the wrong answer.
我们有技术
And we have techniques for
揭示我们错误的方式，我们称之为光学错觉。
revealing the ways in which we get this wrong, and we call them optical illusions.
这是麻省理工学院的Edward Adelson设计的幻觉
So this is an illusion designed by Edward Adelson of MIT.
这里我们有一个棋盘，有白方块和黑方块。
And here we've got a checkerboard with white squares and black squares.
其中两个正方形被标记为A和B。
And two of the squares are labeled A and B.
结果发现这两个正方形的颜色完全相同。
And it turns out those two squares are exactly the same color.
就像你们中的一些人可能会相信我告诉你们的那样，
As some of you may be seeing that you may believe that I'm telling you that,
但你看到的是，一个明显是白色的，一个明显是黑色的。
but you're looking at that and one is clearly white and one is clearly black.
但事实上，它们都是那种颜色，它们都是那种中性灰色。
But in fact they are both that color, they're both that shade of neutral gray.
事实上，如果我把我的正方形覆盖在图片的顶部。
in fact if I overlay my square on top of the picture.
如果A和B是不同的颜色。
If A and B were different colors.
那么你应该会看到一些连续性的中断，对吧，
Then you should see some break in continuity, right,
你应该看到一些边缘形成，但你没有。
you should see some edge forming and you don't.
现在你们中的许多人可能会看到一个渐变。
Now many of you may be seeing a gradient.
谁看到了这里的梯度？
Who is seeing a gradient here?
看着颜色从黑白走向，那就来吧。
Seeing the colors going from black and white, that come on.
是的，是的。
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
你的大脑在骗你，说没有梯度。
Your brain is lying to you, that there's not a gradient.
它是那种颜色，它是一个纯色的正方形。
It is that color, it is a solid colored square.
你知道这个形象的真相，但你仍然不能正确地看到它。
You know the truth of this image and yet you still can't see it correctly.
那是因为卡纳曼没有提到你大脑的另一个部分
It's because there's another part of your brain that Kahneman doesn't talk about
它处理的是反复无常，这是一件非常重要的事情
which deals with inconstancy, which is a really important thing to
因为如果计算机系统变得不一致，
have because if a computer system becomes inconsistent,
它很有可能会失败，对吧？
there's a really good chance it's going to fail, right?
只是[INAUDIBLE]的轰炸声。
It's just [INAUDIBLE] boom.
当生物系统迷惑时，他们不能承受失败的后果。
And biological systems can't afford to fail when they get confused.
所以我们用的是这个系统，它会拒绝信息
So instead we've got this system, which will reject information which is
如果它与我们的内在状态相矛盾，那么它就是通过我们的感官来自这个世界的。
coming from the world through our senses if it contradicts our internal state.
这就是为什么你不能正确地看到这一点。
And that's why you cannot see this correctly.
因为它正在改变你的眼睛所看到的，以便符合
Because it is altering what you are seeing with your eyes in order to conform
你的图像处理模式。
with your patterns of image processing.
事实证明我们一直都在这样做，
And it turns out we do this all the time,
它不仅存在于视觉系统中，它也存在于一切事物中。
it's not just in the visual system, it's in everything.
这就是我们争论的原因
And that's why we argue so
很大程度上是因为我们听不到对方在说什么。
much because we literally cannot hear what the other person is saying.
另一个人说了一些与我们矛盾的话，我们就会
The other person is saying something which contradicts us then we will
曲解了他们说的话，这不是故意的，
misinterpret what they're saying, it's not intentional,
这只是我们为了抵抗矛盾而做的事情的一部分。
it's just part of what we're doing in order to resist inconsistency.
这就是机制。
And this is the mechanism.
所以这一切对广告业来说都不是新闻。
So it turns out none of this was news to the advertising industry.
他们很久以前就发现他们可以
They had figured out a long time ago that they could
设计信息可以绕过直接进入肠道的头部
design messages which would bypass the head that would go straight to the gut
说服我们去买我们不需要的东西。
convincing us that we have to buy things that we don't need.
他们这么做已经很久了
They've been doing this for a long, long time.
Kahneman所做的就是提供理论来解释为什么这样做是可行的。
What Kahneman does is provide the theory which explains why that works.
我认为没有人比烟草业更了解这一点。
And I don't think anybody understood this better than the tobacco industry.
因为你看烟草，好吧，那你怎么卖烟草？
Cuz you look at tobacco, okay, so how do you sell tobacco?
烟草是做什么的？
What what does tobacco do?
它让你闻起来很难闻，它会让你的牙齿变黄，它会让你生病，而且
It makes you smell bad, it turns your teeth yellow, it makes you sick, and
然后它会杀了你。
then it kills you.
那么你如何说服人们，是的，让我们买一些烟草。
So how do you convince people, yeah, let's buy some tobacco.
并且他们通过创建能够混淆系统1的消息来做到这一点。
And they do it by creating messages which are able to confuse system 1.
系统1很容易混淆
System 1 is easily confused
关于缓慢死亡和对你有好处的区别。
about the difference between slow death and good for you.
这就是我们用来编写计算机编程或
So that is the equipment that we have for writing computer programming or
用于编写计算机程序。
for writing computer programs.
程序是人类制造的最复杂的东西。
And programs are the most complicated things that humans make.
在人类经验中，没有任何其他东西是由许多微小的小东西组成的
There's nothing else in human experience which is composed of as many tiny little
所有必须完美结合的片段必须实时工作
pieces which all have to go together perfectly that have to work In real time
在动态情况下改变状态和改变输入。
with changing states and changing inputs in a dynamic situation.
其他任何东西都比不上我们在软件中所拥有的复杂性。
Nothing else comes anywhere close to the complexity that we have in software.
令人惊讶的是，我们能够做到这一点。
And it's amazing that we're able to manage this.
但这真的很难。
But it's really hard.
所以当第一台冯·诺依曼机器开始上线时，
So when the first Von Neumann machine started coming online,
而且发现编程是非常困难的。
and it was discovered programming is really, really difficult.
所以有很多想法，我们需要想出一种方法
So there was a lot of thinking that we need to figure out a way in order to make
更容易。
it easier.
实际上是为了让它变得不必要，因为否则电脑就不多了
In fact to make it unnecessary because otherwise the computers are not much
对我们有用。
use to us.
于是开始了人工智能的研究。
And so that started research in artificial intelligence.
人工智能最初的目标是
And the goal of artificial intelligence originally was to
找出一种让计算机编写自己的程序的方法，
figure out a way to have the computers write their own programs,
因为让人类来写实在是太难了。
because it was just too hard to have humans writing them.
人工智能取得了许多令人惊叹的成功，但他们完全失败了
AI has had a lot of amazing successes but they have failed completely at their
最初的任务，你不能给电脑出问题
original mission, that you cannot give a problem to a computer and
请它编写解决该问题的程序。
ask it to write the program that solves that problem.
如果是的话，我们会问计算机，我们写一个程序
If it were then we would ask the computer, well write a program that's
比你好，一直这样直到他们成为我们的霸主。
better than you and keep doing that until they become our overlords.
而这并没有发生，计算机不知道如何编写程序，所以
And that hasn't happened, computers don't know how to write programs, so
我们给他们写信。
we write them.
所以由于人工智能的失败，
So as a result of the failure of AI,
我们仍在手工编写程序。&gt；&gt；道格拉斯：So
we are still writing programs by hand. &gt;&gt; Douglas: So
我们进行编程最重要的工具是编程语言。
the most important tool we have for doing programming is the programming language.
因为计算机真正擅长的一件事就是翻译一份正式的
Because one thing that computers are really good at, is translating one formal
语言转换成另一种正式语言，这就是编程语言所做的。
language into another formal language and that's what programming languages do.
它们允许我们在越来越高的抽象层次上写作，
They allow us to write at increasing higher levels of abstraction,
在那里我们可以获得更多的杠杆，我们可以用更少的努力创造更多的工作。
where we get more leverage where we can create more work with less effort.
然后计算机或通过编程语言
And then the computer or through the programming language
找出如何将其转换为计算机可以执行的形式。
figures out how to convert it into a form that the computer can execute.
所以编程语言是非常重要的。
And so programming languages are really, really important.
编程之所以如此
The thing that makes programming so
对完美的要求是极其困难的。
extremely difficult is the requirement for perfection.
程序必须在各个方面都绝对完美，
Programs have to be absolutely perfect in every aspect,
对于所有可能的输入，对于所有时间的所有可能的状态，在每个细节中。
in every detail for all possible inputs, for all possible states for all time.
我们与计算机的合同是，如果一个程序
And the contract we have with the computer, is that if a program
并不是在所有这些方面都是完美的，计算机已经被许可做最坏的事情
is not perfect in all of those ways, the computer has licensed to do the worst
在最糟糕的时间可能发生的事情，这不是计算机的错误。
possible thing at the worst possible time and it is not the computer's fault.
这是谁的错？
Whose fault is it?
都是你的错。
It's your fault.
为什么你给了我们一个你知道不完美的程序？
Why did you give us a program which you knew wasn't perfect?
所以你会想得很好，好吧，因为对完美的要求，
So you'd think well okay, because of that requirement for perfection,
我们永远不会发布一个程序到生产，直到我们知道它是完美的。
we would never release a program to production until we know it's perfect.
我们不这么做有两个很好的理由。
And we don't do that for two really good reasons.
第一个是，我们永远不会将程序发布到生产环境中，并且
The first one is, we would never release a program to production, and
最终管理层会发现，或者
eventually management would figure, or
为什么我们要付钱给这些人，他们从来没有完成，让我们想出别的办法。
why are we paying these guys, they never finish, let's figure out something else.
但第二个原因更隐蔽
But the second reason is much more insidious and
那就是我们没有完美的测试。
that is we have no test for perfection.
可能有人曾经创建了一个复杂的程序
It may be that someone once created a complex program
这其实是完美的，没有办法知道。
that actually was perfect, there is no way to know.
没有完美的测试。
There is no test for perfection.
我们有不完美的测试，但没有完美的测试，所以
We have tests for imperfection but no tests for perfection, so
只是无从得知。
there's just no way to tell.
现在，我们的程序很可能没有一个是完美的。
Now, it's most likely that none of our programs are perfect.
因此我们所做的就是将我们的程序投入生产，希望
And so what we do is we put our programs into production hoping that
我们会在其他人发现之前发现它的问题并修复它，
we'll discover what's wrong with it and fix it before anyone else finds out,
这很疯狂，但这是最先进的。
which is crazy, but that is the state of the art.
这是我们找到的最好的方法。
That is the best we have figured out how to do.
所以我们用猎人和采集者的大脑来做这项工作。
So we're doing this work with the brains of hunters and gatherers.
这不是一个比喻。
And this is not a metaphor.
我们的大脑自上一次冰河时代以来就没有进化过。
Our brains have not evolved since the last ice age.
在那次经历中我们没有任何准备
And there was nothing in that experience to have prepared us for
计算机编程。
computer programming.
打猎和采集需要一套完全不同的技能。
Hunting and gathering required a completely different set of skills.
所以，我们能够做到这一点是很令人惊讶的。
So, it's kind of amazing that we're able to do this at all.
这是一种幸运，但在我们的进化中没有任何
It's sort of lucky, but there is nothing in our evolution which
已经为我们做好了准备。
has prepared us for that.
因此，我们正在利用我们所拥有的一切来做这件事。
So we're making use of everything we have in order to do this.
所以编程显然是在利用系统2的头部，因为这就是
So programming obviously is making use of the head, of system 2 because that's where
算法是活生生的，那就是我们做分析工作的地方，
the algorithms live, that's where we do the analytical stuff,
这就是我们在状态和动态中做逻辑的地方，所有这些东西。
that's where we do the logic in the state and the dynamics, all of that stuff.
但我们不知道我们是怎么做到的。
But we don't understand how we do it.
你们都想通了，但是
You have all figured it out but
还不够好，你不能写下一份说明清单。
not well enough that you can write down a list of instructions.
这就是你写计算机程序的方式，你做这些事情，然后
This is how you write a computer program, you do these things, and
把它交给其他人，他们就可以阅读并按照步骤进行操作
hand it to someone else and they can read it and follow the steps and
然后他们就可以写程序了。
then they can write programs.
我们不能这么做。
We can't do that.
不知何故，我们都想通了。
Somehow we have all figured it out.
但还不够好，我们不能告诉别人怎么做。
But not well enough that we could tell someone else how to do it.
这就是为什么我们不能告诉机器怎么做，因为如果我们可以告诉其他人
And that's why we can't tell the machines how to do it because if we can tell other
人类如何做到这一点，然后我们可以告诉机器如何做，但我们不知道。
human how to do it then we can tell machine how to do it, and we don't know.
我们正在做的很多事情
And much of what we're doing
牵涉到直觉，因为我们总是在权衡取舍。
involves intuition because we're always making tradeoffs.
解决问题的最好方法是什么从来都不清楚。
It's never clear what the best approach to solving a problem is going to be.
通常我们试图用不完全的知识来解决问题
And usually we're trying to solve a problem with incomplete knowledge of what
解决之道就在眼前。
the solution is gong to be.
所以我们不得不猜测，系统2不擅长猜测，
And so we have to guess, and system 2 is not good at guessing,
系统1喜欢猜测。
system 1 loves to guess.
系统1会在不知道它在猜测的情况下进行猜测，它很擅长这一点。
System 1 will guess without knowing it's guessing, it's great at that.
所以我们看到一个问题，我们会自上而下地研究它
And so we look at a problem and we'll look at it top down and
自下而上，采取宏观观点和微观观点。
bottom up and take a macro view and micro view.
我们不断地改变我们的观点，直到最终出现一个程序。
We keep constantly shifting our point of view until eventually a program emerges.
我们不知道我们是怎么做到的。
And we don't know how we do that.
所以系统2显然涉及其中，但我认为系统
So system 2 is obviously involved but I think system
1也牵涉其中，这是我们不能记录它的部分原因。
1 is involved there as well, that's part of the reason why we can't document it.
现在我没有证据支持这个论点，但我的直觉告诉我这是真的。
Now I have no evidence to support that argument but my gut tells me it's true.
所以我相信。
So I believe it.